Finding Aid for School of Social Work (University of Michigan) Records 1935-2010
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
- Curriculum, 1967-1994
  - Course Statements
    - Course Statements, 1967-1973
      - 835: Economic Foundations of Social Welfare Policy, 1978-1980 (Box 21)
      - 837: Seminar on Community Intervention, 1977-1979 (Box 21)
      - 838: Formulation and Enactment of Social Welfare Policies, 1977-1980 (Box 21)
      - 845: Assessment Procedures in Interpersonal Practice, 1976-1980 (Box 21)
      - 846: Research Methods in Program Evaluation, 1976-1981 (Box 21)
      - 851: Special Topics, 1977-1979 (Box 21)
      - 852: The Empirically Oriented Practitioner, 1977 (Box 21)
      - 853: Special Topics, 1979-1981 (Box 21)
      - 854: Seminar on Black Families, 1978 (Box 21)
      - 855: Contemporary Research in Alcohol Studies, 1978 (Box 21)
    - Course Statements, 1976-1994
      - 500: Social Welfare Policy and Services, 1976-1982; 2 folders (Box 30)
      - 504: Human Development: Infancy and Childhood, 1977-1981 (Box 30)
      - 505: Human Development: Adolescence, 1977-1981 (Box 30)
      - 506: Ego Psychology I, 1977-1981 (Box 30)
      - 507: Social Role and the Small Group, 1977-1982 (Box 30)
      - 508: Human Behavior: Adulthood, 1977-1978 (Box 30)
      - 509: The Family, 1976-1981 (Box 30)
      - 510: Principles of Behavior Modification, 1977-1984 (Box 30)
      - 511: Human Development: Aging, 1977-1980 (Box 30)
      - 512: Complex Organizations, 1976-1982 (Box 30)
      - 513: Innovation and Change in Social Welfare Organization (Box 30)
      - 514: Community Structure and Processes (Box 30)
      - 515: State and Urban Politics, 1976-1981 (Box 30)
      - 516: Afro-American Culture and Life, 1976-1980 (Box 30)
      - 517: Racism in American Society, 1979-1980 (Box 30)
      - 518: Ethnic Analysis and Social Work Intervention Strategies, 1977-1978 (Box 30)
      - 519: Societal Structure and Process, 1977-1982 (Box 30)
      - 521: Interpersonal Practice I, 1976-1982; 2 folders (Box 30)
      - 522: Introduction to Interpersonal Practice, 1980 (Box 30)
      - 530: Interpersonal Practice Clinical Casework with Individuals and Couples, 1978-1982 (Box 30)
      - 531: Interpersonal Practice with Groups, 1978-1982 (Box 30)
      - 532: Interpersonal Practice with Families and Children, 1978-1982 (Box 30)
      - 535: Behavioral Methods with Families, 1978-1980 (Box 30)
      - 542: Group Work II, 1976 (Box 30)
      - 551: Community Organization I, 1977-1982 (Box 30)
      - 552: Community Practice II, 1976-1977 (Box 30)
      - 553: Social Work in the Black Community, not dated (Box 30)
      - 557: Community Practice Laboratory, 1971 (Box 30)
      - 561: Administration and Policy Methods I, 1977-1980 (Box 30)
      - 562: Policy and Planning, 1977-1980 (Box 30)
      - 573: Grantsmanship and Program Development, 1989 (Box 31)
      - 575: Introduction to Program Evaluation, 1979-1981 (Box 31)
      - 578: Policy and Planning Lab, 1978-1980 (Box 31)
      - 579: Policy and Planning Skill Instruction Laboratory, 1981 (Box 31)
      - 580: Research in Interpersonal Practice, 1982 (Box 31)
      - 581: Research I, 1977-1982 (Box 31)
      - 589: Values and Ethics in Social Work Practice, 1977-1981 (Box 31)
      - 590: Women in Social Work Practice, 1976-1981 (Box 31)
      - 591: Law and Social Work, 1976-1981 (Box 31)
      - 593: Economics of Social Services, 1979-1980 (Box 31)
      - 601: Administration of Justice and Corrections, 1976-1982 (Box 31)
      - 602: Family and Children's Services, 1977-1981; 2 folders (Box 31)
      - 603: Income Maintenance Programs, 1977-1981 (Box 31)
      - 604: Mental Health Problems, 1976-1982 (Box 31)
      - 605: Health and Rehabilitation Program, 1976-1981
      - 608: Programs in Race and Ethnic Relations, 1977-1980 (Box 31)
      - 611: Ego Psychology II, 1976-1981 (Box 31)
      - Practicum Office, 1986-1990 (Box 31)
      - Practicum Student Evaluations, 1991 (Box 31)
      - Professional Practicum, 1983-1994; 4 folders (Box 31)
      - Professional Practicum Students, 1991 (Box 31)
      - Student Liaison Assignment, 1993 (Box 31)
      - Practical Skill Instruction, 1981-1982 (Box 31)
  - Courses Deleted or Discontinued
    - 375-607, 1971-1978 (Box 21)
    - 641-972, 1973-1977 (Box 21)
  - Evaluations
    - 1972-1976 (Box 21)
    - 1977-1979 (Box 21)
    - 1980-1981 (Box 21)
    - Evaluation Related Reports, 1969-1982 (Box 21)
    - Evaluation Summaries, 1972-1980 (Box 21)
    - Student Feedback on Curriculum, 1969-1970 (Box 21)
- Graduate and Doctoral Program, 1948-1989
  Graduate and Doctoral Program, 1948-1989, is composed of minutes, memoranda and supporting materials of the supervising committee, doctoral committee, and admissions, financial aid, and student services committee. These committees worked closely with the process of selecting students into the graduate programs. Some of the material has been classified as restricted and will be closed for seventy-five years from the date of creation due to sensitive material about students.
  - Admissions, Financial Aid and Student Services Committee (AFASS)
    - Admissions Statistics, 1948-1968 (Box 21)
    - Memoranda
      - 1952-1980 (Box 21)
      - 1981-1984 (Box 29)
    - Minutes
      [SR RESTRICTED until July 1, 2059 ]
      - 1951-1955 (Box 29)
        [SR RESTRICTED until July 1, 2030 ]
      - 1956-1958 (Box 29)
        [SR RESTRICTED until July 1, 2033 ]
      - 1959-1962 (Box 29)
        [SR RESTRICTED until July 1, 2037 ]
      - 1963-1977 (Box 29)
        [SR RESTRICTED until July 1, 2052 ]
      - 1978-1984 (Box 29)
    - Supporting Materials, 1969-1977 (Box 21)
  - Coordinating Committee for Social Welfare Research
    - Memoranda, 1955-1960 (Box 21)
    - Minutes
      - 1955-1956 (Box 21)
      - 1957-1960 (Box 21)
    - Proposals, 1955-1958 (Box 21)
    - Reports, 1956-1960 (Box 21)
    - Supporting Materials, 1955-1960 (Box 21)
  - Doctoral Committee
    - Memoranda
      - 1968-1976 (Box 21)
      - 1977-1984 (Box 21)
      - 1984-1987 (Box 21)
      - 1987-1988 (Box 21)
    - Minutes
      - 1968-1977 (Box 21)
      - 1978-1984 (Box 21)
      - 1984-1987 (Box 22)
      - 1987-1989 (Box 22)
    - Reports, Supporting Materials
      - 1959-1975 (Box 22)
      - 1978-1984 (Box 22)
      - 1984-1987 (Box 22)
      - 1987-1989 (Box 22)
    - Doctoral Curriculum, 1972-1986 (Box 22)
  - Supervising Committee
    - Memoranda
      - 1956-1961 (Box 22)
      - 1962-1971 (Box 22)
      - 1972-1987 (Box 22)
    - Minutes
      - 1956-1959 (Box 29)
        [SR RESTRICTED until July 1, 2034 ]
      - 1962-1965 (Box 29)
        [SR RESTRICTED until July 1, 2040 ]
      - 1966-1971 (Box 29)
        [SR RESTRICTED until July 1, 2046 ]
      - 1972-1976 (Box 29)
        [SR RESTRICTED until July 1, 2051 ]
      - 1976-1987 (Box 29)
        [SR RESTRICTED until July 1, 2062 ]
    - Reports and Supporting Materials
      - 1956-1958 (Box 22)
      - 1959-1961 (Box 22)
      - 1962-1967 (Box 22)
      - 1968-1971 (Box 22)
      - 1972-1976 (Box 22)
      - 1978-1987 (Box 22)
- Minority and Student Multicultural Affairs, 1960-1994
  The series Minority and Student Multicultural Affairs, 1960-1994, contains materials documenting minority groups in the School of Social Work. One group which is well documented is Trabajadores de la Raza, a group representing the interests of Latino students in the graduate program.
  - Admissions
    - General, 1977-1990 (Box 23)
    - Admissions Committee, 1971 (Box 23)
    - Financial Aid and Student Services Committee, 1974-1978 (Box 23)
  - Affirmative Action, 1987-1988 (Box 23)
  - Association of Black Social Work Students (ABSWS), 1975-1986 (Box 23)
  - Minority Opportunities Committee
    - Annual Reports, 1971-1980 (Box 23)
    - Association of Black Social Work Students Report, circa 1973 (Box 23)
    - Chicano Training Center, 1973-1975 (Box 23)
    - Classes and Courses Pertaining to Minority Students, 1972-1975 (Box 23)
    - Doctoral Program, 1972-1974 (Box 23)
    - Doctoral Section of 1972 Reaccreditation Report (Box 23)
    - International Students, 1980-1981 (Box 23)
    - Maintaining and Increasing Minority Enrollment, a report, 1972 (Box 23)
    - Memoranda, 1970-1982 (Box 23)
    - Minority Opportunity at the University of Michigan School of Social Work, 1971 (Box 23)
    - Minority Relevant Content
      - 1966-1974 (Box 23)
      - 1973 (Box 23)
      - 1975-1976 (Box 23)
      - 1979-1980 (Box 23)
    - Minutes, 1970-1981 (Box 23)
    - Questionnaire, 1977 (Box 23)
    - Recruitment, Admission and Financial Aid, 1970-1972 (Box 24)
    - Reports
      - 1967-1979 (Box 24)
      - 1973-1976 (Box 24)
    - Student Organizations and Recruitment Proposals, 1973 (Box 24)
    - Student Survey, 1980-1981 (Box 24)
    - Sub-Committee on Minority Enrollment, 1979-1980 (Box 24)
    - Women, 1971-1972 (Box 24)
  - National Association of Black Social Workers, 1978 (Box 24)
  - Recruitment, Admissions, and Financial Aid Committee (RAFA)
    - Minutes
      - 1992-1993 (Box 24)
      - 1993-1994 (Box 24)
    - Reports, 1968-1970 (Box 24)
  - Trabajadores de la Raza
    - Chicano Brown Paper, 1970-1972 (Box 24)
    - Chicano Recruitment Manual, circa 1980 (Box 24)
    - Correspondence, 1976-1981 (Box 24)
    - Donations, 1978 (Box 24)
    - Financial Aid, 1977 (Box 24)
    - Minutes, 1976-1981 (Box 24)
    - Miscellaneous, 1973-1981 (Box 24)
    - Recruitment
      - 1970-1973 (Box 24)
      - 1973-1977 (Box 24)
      - 1978-1980 (Box 24)
    - Recruiting Guidelines, undated (Box 24)
- Student Placement and Statistics, 1935-1978
  Student Placement and Statistics, 1935-1978 consists mainly of lists of students enrolled in the graduate program. The lists offer a brief glimpse at the composition of the student body in the early years of the program. In addition, the files show where the students were placed to work while they were in the program.
  - Enrollment Reports
    - 1935-1955 (Box 24)
    - 1955-1968 (Box 24)
    - 1969-1977 (Box 24)
    - 1978-1983 (Box 25)
  - Roster of Students-Detroit, 1951-1954 (Box 25)
  - Roster of Students in Course at Michigan State Normal College, 1950 (Box 25)
  - Field Instruction Agencies, 1953-1966 (Box 25)
  - Field Work Placements
    - 1952-1960 (Box 25)
    - 1960-1965 (Box 25)
    - 1965-1966 (Box 25)
    - 1966-1967 (Box 25)
    - 1968 (Box 25)
    - 1969-1970 (Box 25)
- Winkelman and Fauri Lectures Series, 1965-1996
  The Winkelman and Fauri Lectures Series, 1951-1958, 1965-1966, is composed of the correspondence surrounding the planning of these two annual lectures. Many of the lectures were published and can be found in the publications finding aid which immediately follows this finding aid. Some of the transcripts are also available online (http://www.ssw.umich.edu/outreach.html). The Leon and Josephine Winkelman Memorial Lecture Series focuses on issues of aging and gerontology. The Fedele F. and Iris M. Fauri Memorial Lecture in Child Welfare is presented annually in recognition of former Dean Fedele F. Fauri and his wife. U.S. Congressman Sander Levin and Donna Shalala, U.S. Secretary of Health and Human Services, have been some of the notable speakers for the Fauri series. Also included in this series is a file of speeches made by Fedele Fauri from 1951 to 1958.
  - Winkelman Foundation, 1965 (Box 27)
  - Winkelman General Information, 1974-1993 (Box 27)
  - Winkelman Lecture Series
    - Prof. Zena Smith Blau, 1978 (Box 27)
    - Dr. Daniel C. Hadlock, 1979 (Box 27)
    - Dr. Barbara Soloman, 1980 (Box 27)
    - Dr. Bernice L. Neugarten, 1981 (Box 27)
    - Prof. Bend Rold Andersen, 1982 (Box 27)
    - Dr. Matilda White Riley, 1983 (Box 27)
    - Dr. Gabe J. Maletta, 1984 (Box 27)
    - Dr. Mildred M. Seltzer, 1986 (Box 27)
    - Dr. Theodore Goldberg, 1987 (Box 27)
    - Dr. Gary Andrews, 1988 (Box 27)
    - John H. Pickering, 1989 (Box 27)
    - Olivia P. Maynard, 1990 (Box 27)
    - Dr. Gene D. Cohen, 1992-1993 (Box 27)
    - Dr. Ronald J. Angel, 1994 (Box 27)
    - Dr. Herbert A. Rosefield, Jr., 1995 (Box 27)
    - Dr. W. Andrew Achenbaum, 1996 (Box 27)
  - Fauri Lecture General Information (Box 27)
  - Fauri Lecture Series
    - Dr. Winifred Bell, 1985 (Box 27)
    - Dr. Peter W. Forsythe, 1986 (Box 27)
    - Dr. Alvin F. Poussaint, 1987 (Box 27)
    - Honorable Rosemary Barkett, 1988 (Box 27)
    - Jonathon Kozol, 1990 (Box 27)
    - Ruth W. Massinga, 1990 (Box 27)
    - Honorable Sander M. Levin, 1992-1993 (Box 27)
    - Dr. James K. Whittaker, 1994 (Box 27)
    - Prof. Sheila B. Kamerman, 1994 (Box 27)
    - Prof. Richard P. Barth, 1995 (Box 27)
  - Videotape of Dr. Gene P. Cohen Lecture on VHS, 1992 (Box 27)
- Personnel, 1954-1968
  The series Personnel, 1954-1968, contains information on faculty members, the majority of which are deceased. Most folders include some type of obituary in addition to information about their time as a faculty member. The most interesting is the file of Wilbur J. Cohen, who was appointed as Assistant Secretary for Legislation in the Department of Health, Education, and Welfare by President Kennedy in 1961, and who later became Secretary of HEW. In addition, Cohen served as dean for the School of Education from 1969 to 1978.
  - Anton, Thomas J. (Box 28)
  - Bar-gal, David (Box 28)
  - Bechill, William D. (Box 28)
  - de Bruyn, M (Box 28)
  - Cohen, Wilbur J. (Box 28)
  - Cook, Loraine M. (Box 28)
  - Cox, Fred M. (Box 28)
  - Cranefield, Eleanor (Box 28)
  - Crowthers, Virginia L. (Box 28)
  - Dinsmore, Merle L. (Box 28)
  - Fauri, Fedele F. (Box 28)
  - Fletcher, Ralph Carr (Box 28)
  - Fraiberg, Selma H. (Box 28)
  - Goodman, Sylvia E. (Box 28)
  - Gottfried, Lenore (Box 28)
  - Himle, David (Box 28)
  - Jones, Charles (Box 28)
  - Kelso, Robert W. (Box 28)
  - Kim, Stanley S. (Box 28)
  - Kroman, Lenore J. (Box 28)
  - Lazarus, Mitchel J. (Box 28)
  - Lind, Roger M. (Box 28)
  - Litwak, Eugene (Box 28)
  - Locher, Ruth A. (Box 28)
  - Pinkus, Helen S. (Box 28)
  - Portner, Faye (Box 28)
  - Rabinovitz, Patricia W. (Box 28)
  - Resnick, Herman (Box 28)
  - Riley, John M. (Box 28)
  - Robinson, Dorothy (Box 28)
  - Rosen, Helen (Box 28)
  - Schaeger, Jules (Box 28)
  - Schroeder, Dorothy (Box 28)
  - Segal, Robert M. (Box 28)
  - Shapiro, E. Donald (Box 28)
  - Sundel, Martin (Box 28)
  - Vasey, Wayne (Box 28)
  - Wagner, Hartmut (Box 28)
  - Watkins, Elizabeth (Box 28)
- Faculty Committee on the Presidency, 1978-1979
  The Faculty Committee on the Presidency series (.3 linear feet) is restricted for thirty years from the date of creation. These materials are records of a Faculty Senate appointed committee which reviewed the needs of the University of Michigan and considered various candidates for the presidential search in 1978-1979. Harold Johnson served as chairman of this committee.
  - Membership Lists, 1978 (Box 29)
  - Minutes, 1978-1979 (Box 29)
    - Correspondence (Box 29)
    - General, 1978-1979 (Box 29)
    - Regents, 1978-1979 (Box 29)
  - Needs Statements
    - Departmental, 1978 (Box 29)
    - Committee Drafts, 1978 (Box 29)
  - Nominations, 1978-1979; 2 folders (Box 29)
  - Interviewing Team, 1979 (Box 29)
  - Clippings, 1978-1979 (Box 29)
- Dean's Files, 1947-1987
  The Dean's Files (1 linear foot, 1947-1987) series is comprised solely of materials from the office of Dean Fedele Fauri. Materials in this series include a small amount of biographical materials, correspondence (incoming and outgoing), and photographs. The series does contain one document, Lifetime Achievement Award Certificate, presented posthumously in November 1987 by the Michigan League for Human Services. The most extensive materials in the series are speeches presented by Fauri in the various positions he held, including Dean, Director of the Michigan Department of Social Welfare, and Senior Specialist in Social Welfare and Social Security of the Legislative Reference Service in Washington D.C. The majority of the speeches are based on social welfare themes including social security, old-age and survivors insurance coverage and dependent children. The speeches were given to a wide variety of audiences and at a number of locations across the country as well as cities throughout Michigan. The series also includes Fauri's report The Tax Freeze of the Old-Age and Survivors Insurance Program Since 1939, prepared for the Senate Finance Committee in 1947, and a report prepared for the Council on Social Work Education dated March 1963.
  - Miscellaneous, 1947-1987
    - Awards, 1951-1987 (Box 32)
    - Biographical, 1951-1971 (Box 32)
    - Correspondence
      - Committee on Ways and Means, 1951-1954 (Box 32)
      - Congratulatory, 1970-1971 (Box 32)
      - General, 1973-1975; 2 folders (Box 32)
      - Social Security Administration, 1951 (Box 32)
    - News clippings, ca., 1947-1951; 2 folders (Box 32)
    - Photographs and not dated, 1958 (Box 32)
    - Publications, 1954-1964 (Box 32)
    - Report
      - Council on Social Work Education, March 1963 (Box 32)
      - (Report of the) Onsite Evaluation Team, April 25-27, 1973 (Box 32)
      - Study of Employment Security Administration Costs (draft), January 2, 1953 (Box 32)
      - The Tax Freeze of the Old-Age and Survivors Insurance Program Since 1939, June 19, 1947 (Box 32)
    - Scrapbooks, ca., 1940-1943; 3 folders (Box 32)
      (note: scrapbooks are in poor condition)
    - Speeches
      - 1951 (Box 32)
      - 1952-1954 (Box 32)
      - 1955-1957 (Box 32)
      - 1960 (Box 32)
      - 1961 (Box 32)
      - 1962 (Box 32)
      - 1963 (Box 33)
      - 1964 (Box 33)
      - 1965 (Box 33)
      - 1966 (Box 33)
      - 1967 (Box 33)
      - 1968-1969 (Box 33)
      - 1970-1973 (Box 33)
- Doctoral Program, 1982-1989
  Graduate and Doctoral Program series (.1 linear feet, 1982-1989) while sparse, does contain a few supervisory committee meeting minutes from 1982-1988, which reflect the doctoral application and candidate review process as well as student recruitment efforts. The materials also provide a summary of applicants admitted for selected academic years. The series is a continuation of earlier accessions.
  - Procedures and Background materials, 1982-1989 (Box 33)
  - Supervisory Committee Meeting Minutes, 1982-1988 (Box 33)
- Institute of Labor and Industrial Relations, 1980-1994
  Institute of Labor and Industrial Relations (ILIR) (.50 linear feet, 1980-1994), consists of a limited number of records relating to the ILIR. This particular period reflects a transition period for the ILIR as it separated from its original joint partnership with Wayne State University to governance held jointly by the deans of the School of Social Work and School of Business Administration. The official change in governance occurred in 1993. Significant documentation in the series includes a selection of Executive Board minutes (1985-1990) and Internal Review Board minutes (1980-1981). Lastly, the reports Review of the Institute of Labor and Industrial Relations (1981) and the Report on the Future of the Institute of Labor and Industrial Relations (1993) provide an excellent snapshot of the Institute's mission and goals for this time period. Note that earlier material created by the Institute of Labor and Industrial Relations is available at the Bentley Historical Library. See Institute of Labor and Industrial Relations (University of Michigan -- Wayne State University) records, 1949-1975.
  - Annual Reports, 1983-1988 (Box 33)
  - Certificate Program, 1981-1984 (Box 33)
  - Correspondence, 1982-1993 (Box 33)
  - Executive Board Minutes, 1985-1990 (Box 33)
  - Historical Background, Report, "Facing the Changing World of Work: The Program of the Institute of Labor and Industrial Relations,", May 1981 (Box 33)
  - Internal Review Committee, 1980-1981 (Box 33)
  - Personnel, 1984-1994 (Box 33)
  - Report
    - Future of the Institute of Labor and Industrial Relations, 1993 (Box 33)
    - Future of Labor Studies at the University of Michigan: Proposed Strategic Directions, March 1989 (Box 33)
    - Strategic Education Program for the Michigan Construction Industry, May 1990 (Box 33)
  - Research, 1982-1994 (Box 33)
  - Review Committee Report, August 6, 1981 (Box 33)
  - Responses to the Review Committee Report, September 8, 1981 (Box 33)
  - Staff Profiles, 1993 (Box 33)
  - Strategic Planning, Background Materials, 1987-1994 (Box 33)
  - Women and Work Program, 1984 (Box 33)
- Archived School of Social Work Website
  The Archived Website series documents the academic programs, accomplishments, resources, events, and people at the School of Social Work. Content includes important news and announcements, publications (such as newsletters and course catalogs), and information about admissions, curriculum, degree requirements, faculty, and the overall mission of the School. The website series is arranged chronologically, with captures from 2002 and 2003 stored on CD. Starting in 2010, this archived website will be captured on a regular, ongoing basis as part of the University of Michigan Web Archives, hosted at http://webarchives.cdlib.org/a/universityofmichigan/.
  - Home Page
    - 1996-1998
      (These versions were preserved by the Internet Archive and are made available through its Wayback Machine. The Bentley Historical Library is not involved in the collection or maintenance of this material.)
    - 1998-[ONGOING]
    - May 22, 2003, .ZIP file
    - March 7, 2006, .ZIP file
    - May 13, 2008, .ZIP file
    - 2010-[ONGOING]
  - Related Materials: degree requirements curricula, research, centers, and institutes, 2010-[ONGOING]